<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data date-time-format="iso8601">
	<event start="1199-04-06" title="Death of King Richard">Richard died of gangrene from a wound suffered while asserting his right of treasure-trove over the minor lord of the castle of Chalus in Limousin. He bequeathed his crown and his "Angevin Empire" to his brother John.</event>
	<event start="1199-04-18" title="Arthur proclaimed rightful successor to Richard">On Easter, the barons of Brittany, Anjou, Maine, and Touraine accepted John's nephew Arthur as Richard's successor. Arthur was but twelve, and his mother, Constance of Brittany, placed him under the protection of Philip of France while she raised forces against John</event>
	<event start="1199-05-27" title="John crowned king of England"/>
    <event start="1199-06-29" end="1200-02-24" isDuration="true" title="John in France">When John succeeded his brother Richard, his throne was not at all secure.&lt;p&gt; The supporters of John's nephew, Arthur of Brittany. fomented rebellion in France with the support of Philip Augustus</event>
    <event start="1200-02-27" end="1200-04-28" isDuration="true" title="John in England"/>
    <event start="1200-05-02" end="1200-10-01" isDuration="true" title="John in France"/>
    <event start="1200-10-06" end="1201-05-14" isDuration="true" title="John in England"/>
    <event start="1201-06-02" end="1203-12-05" isDuration="true" title="John in France"/>
    <event start="1200-05-22" title="Treaty of le Goulet">Philip acknowledges John as the rightful heir to the continental lands held by his father and brother, and John acknowledges Philip as his overlord for those lands.</event>
     <event start="1200-08-24" title="Married Isabell of Angoulême">In 1176, Henry II had betrothed John to Isabelle of Gloucester and their marriage took place in 1189, much to the horror of the church for Isabelle was John's cousin. This consanguinity was the basis for John's divorce, probably in 1200. Seeking an alliance that would bolster his continental interests, John now married Isabelle of Angoulême, the daughter of Count Aymer. By this marriage, however, John alienated Hugh le Brun, lord of Lusignan to whom Isabelle had been engaged. The Lusignans were extremely influential in the Angevin dominions in the south and this insult was to drive them into the arms of Philip Augustus. As John's lord by the treaty of le Goulet, Philip was obliged to call John to account for this and other abuse of his vassals the Lusignans. It was this feudal and familial conflict which was the proximate cause of the loss of Normandy in 1204.</event>
     <event start="1202-08-01" icon="../Images/battle.png" title="Relief of the siege at Mirebeau">John's mother, Eleanor, is besieged at Mirebeau by the supporters of Arthur. Appearing as if from nowhere, as his father and brother used to do, John joined With William des Roches, seneschal of Anjou, and after a forced march of 80 miles or more, John captured the besiegers in their sleep including Geoffrey de Lusignan who was, unsuspecting, in the middle of his breakfast of pigeons.&lt;p&gt;Exultant, John writes to England: &lt;blockquote&gt;Know that by the grace of God we are safe and well and God's mercy had worked wonderfully with us, for on Tuesday before the feast of St Peter ad Vincula, when we were on the road to Chinon, we heard that the lady our mother was closely besieged at Mirebeau, and we hurried there as fast as we could, arriving on the feast of St Peter ad Vincula. And there we captured our nephew Arthur, whom William de Briouze delivered to us, and Geoffrey de Lusignan, Hugh le Brun, Andrew de Chauvigni, and the viscount of Châteleraut, Raymond Touars, Savary de Mauléon, Hugh Baugé, and all our other Poitevin enemies who were there, being upwards of two hundred knights, and none escaped. Therefore God be praised for our happy success.&lt;/blockquote&gt; (ref. Coggeshall, pp. 137-8; as quoted in &lt;cite&gt;King John&lt;/cite&gt; by W. L. Warren.)</event>
     <event start="1202-03-26" title="Venerabilem fratrem nostrum" icon="../Images/papal-cross.png">Innocent III's decretal &lt;a href="http://legalhistorysources.com/ChurchHistory220/Lecture%20Four/InnocentIIIChurchState.html"&gt;Venerabilem fratrem nostrum&lt;/a&gt;</event>
          <!--  in a typically legalistic vein, found a way to favor the election of Otto IV, John's kinsman at the expense of Phillip Hoenstauffen in the disputed election of the German Emperor. Subsequent events suggest that this may have encouraged John to imagin that the Pope would weigh in in his favor -->
    <event start="1203-04-22" title="The murder of Arthur?">&lt;blockquote&gt;After King John had captured Arthur and kept him alive in prison for some time, at length, in the castle of Rouen, after dinner on the Thursday before Easter, when he was drunk and possessed by the devil, he slew him with his own hand, and tying a heavy stone to the body cast it into the Seine. It was discovered by a fisherman in his net, and being dragged to the bank and recognised, was taken for secret burial, in fear of the tyrant, to the priory of Bec called Notre Dame des Prés&lt;/blockquote&gt; (ref. &lt;cite&gt;Annals of Margam&lt;/cite&gt;, p. 27)</event>
     <event start="1203-12-05" title="John abandons Normandy"/>

</data>
